so
the first retina discussion
how shall we proceed does anyone have
any particularly interesting
notes to start out with
so we are discussing the first video
that you reckon yes
we are discussing the first conversation
that john had with
um jordan hall on the design constraints
for the religion that's not a religion
are you recording now yes
no one has any particularly interesting
thingies so
one thing that sort of jumped out at me
was
because because i haven't been doing
this in my head at least
is that john thinks
that we should work out the
functionality of religion
in the first place like get a really
full understanding of religion and
spirituality and how it works
and then reverse engineer that
back into um
yeah like the root now and
i guess on the chat the text channel so
far we haven't
sort of discussed the functionality of
religion too much
so far like we obviously we do because
it's just necessary but
it feels like maybe we should put more
focus on that
uh
well i i think
it sounds almost to me like this the
issue is very similar but
or the issues are very similar but
they're actually two different
um because the definition and the
function isn't necessarily the same
thing
and so i guess the question then is i
don't remember actually in the video i
remember the function stuff i don't
remember the definition stuff so i guess
that
i didn't mean to say definition i just
meant i may have misspoke
no no it's shivarani who's saying
definition
yeah so
and then we've got to say okay so what
are we trying to create
and then we can create it right but i
think that has
like um there's two particular ways of
talking about the problem
like on the one hand um
we already have the answer in that we
are looking for a religion that's not a
religion but we don't have the answer
because we don't know
which religion that's not a religion we
need so
i don't know if you are talking trying
to speak about the more broad one or the
more narrow one
in that case
like i mean i presume that you agree
with the idea that
we need a religion that's not a religion
are you talking to chef around either
yeah
sorry yeah i think i i think by
definition we all agree that we need a
religion that's not a religion
yeah so then the i think that like the
the problem then is
is creating the religion that's not a
religion and then from there
the functionality question is the first
one that arises because we ask ourselves
well what exactly is it that religions
do right
well look what what i heard and maybe i
misheard but what i heard was what
problems
are you trying to solve with the
religion that is not a religion
and so defining those problems
specifically would
be the first step and then it sounded to
me like
again from what i heard the second step
is figuring out
how those problems are currently or
should be currently addressed
uh with with existing religions
and then the third step from what i
heard was to reverse
engineer that right and then and then
you can have the basis for doing the
creation
and the the the the problem that i'm
hearing is
okay so that and just to be clear
because i don't want to
you know i'm not trying to hide anything
but what i keep hearing
is yeah that's not a religion so let's
just design it
but we're not taking those first three
steps and so i think
that focusing on on maybe at least one
of those steps and you don't necessarily
have to do them
uh in order to get the definitions down
but probably in order is better right
would be would be helpful so for example
you could go through all the things you
think religions do
and not worry about targeting it towards
you know some specific
aspect that you may may not be able to
define in terms of problem to fix
prior so you know
pick one and let's work on that first
and see how far we can get what notes we
can take etc
and how does that sound agreed
and that sort of uh made me think
because later on john says that the
whole
is a fair point like we need to
formulate the problem
really really well before we can start
to solve
things and it occurs to me that
understanding the functionality of
religion and formulating the problem
are basically the same thing because if
we've lost
religion and now we're in a meaning
crisis
the problem is that we've lost the
functionality of religion
so
yeah i think i can agree with that yeah
it was well i mean one of the things
that i also wrote down is the importance
that you know
uh nietzsche was pronouncing the death
of god
but he was doing so while he fully
understood what we were losing in terms
of the functionality
to your point
all right so um could we say that to the
degree that we're all gathered here
speaking
together with each other that we're
hoping collectively to produce
something of value with regards to
understanding this process
and then could we not say that that
which feeds into
that product this very process itself
should kind of exemplify
those elements of collective wisdom that
are
if not tangential directly
representative of the religion it's not
a religion so
is there a manner in which we could be
now in each other's presence
as we set an intention and as we develop
this stuff in real time
that is uh at the same time that it's
constructing it
or representing it right is there
something that is
true to that process which is part of
what we're trying to build
and that we can notice uh as a part of
the design criteria
i feel like we consistently
engage in you know dialogue us
like a lot so i think we all we
we just do that anyway
but that reminds me what me and mark
was saying yesterday well it's what mark
brought up um
a lot of us on the written our committee
aren't don't seem to be doing
the like community practice on the
discord
like almost at all like there's almost
no overlap between written our committee
and the people who are regularly doing
practices
so like that i feel like that's relevant
to the idea of us
exemplifying what we're going to try and
do in the end while we do it
especially as they'll probably make us
give wiser answers to the problems
yes um we probably should be doing that
um sometimes i do and sometimes i don't
and i'm bad at consistent
well nothing wrong with partaking in the
events
what not but question in there is
which of the events particularly geared
towards narrative
we have an ecology of practices
springing from primarily the meditation
series
right and and we've been uh trying to
implement those
as best as we can and we've been
modifying them right and we're trying to
document all that at the same time and
we
haven't been doing a good job of that
but we we have some it's not like we
haven't done any
and participation in at least the stuff
john's talking about in terms of
ecologies is useful
participating on the discord server is
probably
as useful if not more useful because
some of our practices vary
right because they're more around
communities because that's more what
we're trying to build here
i i don't know why we would limit it to
narratives since we don't actually know
what
does and doesn't work and we haven't
schematized the ecology of practices yet
although
i'm looking forward to talking to john
about that in the next couple of weeks
and then i'm i'm not sure
how relevant that is to problem
definition for example so while i think
this is a good effort and yeah we did
talk about it last night and
it's definitely uh something to put on
the list
i think that we can actually make
progress with the definition
if we focus on the definition of the
problem we're trying to solve
and just get step one sort of at least
on the tracks
if not uh if if not far enough down the
track to
to be useful
and i will add uh one of the notes i
made which i already believed i think
i've said it already
i think trying to do narrative
right now is a bit you know ahead of
ourselves
feels like it should probably emerge out
of
like an established set of practices and
and stuff like that like that that
should come first and it feels like we
haven't
gotten anywhere near that yet no but
my whole uh perspective on this is the
narrative is the functionality that
religion
affords people so
uh you know yeah we well um
you might say that we're trying to get
ahead of us ourselves by dealing with
narrative but i think
that actually narrative is what we
should be looking at first of all
when we're trying to figure out the
functionality of religion
i don't know i i think there's something
subtle that goes on during the practice
of education
where you you construct your own inner
narrative regardless of what is
spoken about culturally at the meta
layer
and i think if we have an ecology
practices and if we have
sets of information which are sufficient
to explain
a lot of these deeply important aspects
of life and cognition
and communitas and all of that then
if you let people look out in the world
at the the sum total of all the
narratives
they'll see the common threads
themselves and
from that perhaps construct something
which is convergent enough with other
people who have gone through that same
process
such that they can use a common language
but not require
that everyone have precisely the same
words or precisely the same
narrative right it's just that it's
mapping onto
a common experience to a sufficient
level right
yeah it's like it feels like like
yes we need narrative like we do yeah oh
but
that needs content like it's gonna have
to refer yeah
and if we're looking at narrative in the
terms of defining functionality
and um looking at then we're looking at
um
other religions narratives we're not
figuring out our own we're trying to
figure out okay how does this religion's
narrative work how does this religion's
narrative work
okay what's the commonalities what's the
differences
right i agree but the only way that
we're going to be able to do that is by
in some sense practicing the narrative i
think
no that's not practice that's um looking
at this and examining it unless you're
talking about practicing the narratives
of other religions
because at this point we're not create
you're not creating your own you're
saying i need to better understand the
problem
i need to better understand what's going
on already okay how do other narratives
work how do other religions work
what's the problem we're trying to solve
okay now that we've got the problem
figured out
what divided into sections okay now
we've got sections let's work on the
section
yeah so we're still at the process we
haven't even
started exploring the narratives of any
religions yet and we need to do that
that's i think what my position well i'm
definitely on board with that
i just feel like um like we're gonna
have to kind of
sort out if you want to know what i mean
like pretty much everything else first
and then the narrative will grow out and
bind everything
all together in the end it feels like
rather than the narrative coming first
and then everything coming from the
narrative
well given that we're going to have to
look into all these things anyway i'd
say if strewn wants to
examine narrative and start looking into
that in depth then that makes sense and
he can do that and
get back to us and let us know what he's
figured out
yeah yeah well i mean the the comments
in the
ritmail section about heroism and what
is basically
where i am on that front so i mean like
i'm happy to share with with what i've
discovered um
but i don't know if that really counts
as a practice or some something that the
retinal community is doing as a
collective or like a communal project
so then well um you know
i would be doing that on my own but then
what would the rest of you be doing
yeah well from my understanding that
what we'd want to do is we want to have
um different sections what are different
groups of us working on different things
um and if um if exploring narrative is
something you're really interested in
then it makes sense for you to be
heading up that section
and then um we want other people looking
at
other aspects of the problem right
yeah fair enough i suppose if we can so
long as we can get everything
working together in some sort of
reasonable fashion
think of it as a really big group
project and we're having to divide into
subgroups
it's a good idea but we should all
definitely keep our sort of
fingers in every domain and not just
sort of
split up and then just come back to
pretty much dictate to each other what
we found in the
different areas because only we are
familiar with our area or whatever
just sort of specialize rather than like
completely go in on one thing
yeah so maybe um well we're doing these
weekly meetings maybe
have like okay this is what i'm going to
try and get done this week this is what
i'm going to try and get done this week
and then we get when we meet up we say
okay what have you
figured out okay what have you figured
out and then discuss the different
um parts that get brought up
yeah so certainly a standard project
management practice is to
report on what you got done last week in
your section
right and then you know to your point
report on what you're
moving forward with and just to keep
everybody up to date
in a quick you know i mean if you're
doing software it would be called agile
although
you know it's perfectly perfectly
reasonable to do it weekly
um if it's quick then
everybody can stay up to date and then
as long as we're tracking things in the
appropriate channels or whatever then
people have text to refer to and we can
come up with outlines or reports or
you know whatever we need to circulate
for more detail for those who are
interested
okay so what other subsections do we
need right now
so strewn was mentioning he um
he's interested in looking into
narrative and
looking at the narrative of religion
what other things do we need to
prioritize looking at right now
well there's the obvious ecology of
practices and
kind of because i i i'm under the
impression that
mark and ben and others
i assume are really really sort of
going in on trying to make a little
prototype of
our ecology of practices
define the problem first though like
this the
um we could be exploring um different
practices and figuring out okay this is
useful for this this is useful for this
but until we know okay so the problem is
x
we don't know okay will the ecology
a help with x and so you can do all
kinds of research on ecology a but if
it's not going to help with x
[Music]
then
yeah so if you if you want to do a uh
targeted approach
then the problem definition has to come
before any of the other work
and again i'm you know not opposed to
doing that or
the alternative is you know go after the
big three
all at the same time in parallel right
so that's problem definition
uh you know what what we're expecting
out of
uh written r to to solve that problem
and
what we can steal from existing
religious practices
at the same time it's it's a lot harder
to steal from the religious practices at
least in theory if you have to go after
after everything before the problem
definition is done but i i'm not sure
that
you wouldn't have to do that anyway so
um
yeah we still need the problem
definition either way i think
that has to be high on the list yeah we
higher priority but
definitely by looking at practices it
will give us
pointers about what problems to solve
yeah well we're not we're not if it's a
big problem right that's what i'm saying
is so
um that part of the problem is that the
existing religions aren't working okay
so why are the
existing religions working what are the
existing religions giving and what are
they lacking
all right so we've got that sorted out
okay
what is the um what is the
problems that people are having in their
everyday life are that um
meaning problems with meaning in
everyday life with the
work-life balance or anything like that
okay so
what of what else is causing a problem
what else is related to the problem what
else is part of the problem
this comes back to some notes i made on
the video
so partly because of strewn
basically i think we could
um have a very general overview of the
problem
as we've basically totalized
truth and we've lost relevance
and it seems to me that you call it that
all the practices
in they pretty much
are for calibrating your relevance
systems as opposed to your truth systems
and then a kind of sub problem is of
that
is that even when people
do kind of recognize the importance of
relevance
it's usually then at the expense of
truth so you've got the opposite problem
and they're not integrated properly
so i can't exactly remember where i was
going with that but there you are
well i think there's quite a bit of
truth in that actually
i don't know if you john just released
another video
um he was talking about well he was he
was doing a video on the
the people who do the mars rover work
but he was really really in depth with
respect to the perspective on knowing
and the predatory knowing
that kind of thing and he's also
starting to make that distinction
between
or at least in that video he made the
distinction between reality and realness
where reality was you know some kind of
ontological state but the realness was
the
was the feeling of something being
worthwhile that
and so yeah i think that's actually a
good direction to be going down
and i think we can see john is also
starting to go down
so did anyone have any particular
thoughts on the
comments about the iron age hierarchies
in the video
don't think i had anything deep on it
pretty much just i agree that we should
probably avoid
them and that they're probably
responsible
partly for the
descent into just dead propositions
i'd argue for not a hierarchy as such
but um uh some people are
better at teaching some things and some
better people are better at doing other
things
and so then you'll kind of have uh all
right so
um this person's really good at yoga and
this person's really good at tai chi so
if i want to learn tai chi i'll go to
this person if i want to learn yoga i'll
go to this person
so not so much a hierarchy as such as uh
um different people for different tasks
i guess we want to avoid the triangular
hierarchy where it's all just
goes up to some pinnacle at the top
where there's one or very small number
of people
just sort of in command of everybody
but we don't want to just demolish all
authority of any kind
so we sort of want
a landscape with bumps that rise up out
of it
basically so that each bump isn't
necessarily you know
controlled by some supreme pinnacle
you are not the best but you're better
at this than me so i'll i can learn from
you
what did you think stroke um
it's complicated on the one hand yes but
on the other hand
like the state is an authority
where it has a monopoly on violence and
at the end of the day the disagree like
violence is the ultimate decider in
terms of this
if you're willing to get violent then
you're going to win out of the person
that isn't um
and i think like on the one hand yes we
don't want an iron age hierarchy where
everything goes narrow to the top but on
the other hand
you have to have some kind of
centralizing feature that at least can a
that is able to constrain
you know human behavior such as violent
behavior to a reasonable degree
because if you don't have that then
you're just going to have an anarchy so
we we can't just do away with the
hierarchy completely but
we need to figure out a way of
reconceptualizing it so that it doesn't
repeat the the worst uh
features of what we can see in the ina
hierarch
wouldn't community expectation of um
of non-violence be sufficient
uh no because you already have laws
against murder
but people still do it anyway and then
when it happens you have to
actually have somebody to take care of
the the the consequences in the fallout
and that invariably involves something
like a justice
and so that entire system has to work
so we're not we're not recreating
community we've already got community
we've already got justice systems
those are in place in lots of different
countries we're not creating a new
universal country with universal laws
and universal enforcement
we're just creating a new way of looking
at things and a
new way of that relevance realization
work
no but well i i frankly i disagree
because
the entire the fact that the two worlds
model is collapsing and we can no longer
believe in our religions
is also undermining the philosophical
basis
which we use to justify these various
legal systems the one doesn't
to lose credibility in the one is
ultimately to see the other one as like
some kind of
arbitrary contrivance it doesn't make
sense and that causes
if if you can't ground those systems
in such a way that the person can
actually integrate with those systems in
terms of their world view
then there will be a clash and the the
people will fundamentally start to
undermine
or subvert the the authorities and that
will lead ultimately to a societal
collapse
and so from my perspective ultimately
what you need rick lars to do is to be
able to be robust enough
to to actually sustain something like a
legal system
because if it doesn't do that then it's
not it fundamentally won't be viable in
my opinion
so you're figuring society is going to
collapse so we want to build something
that can take its place
um well i i wouldn't want to say it's
different
to collapse but there are several
indicators that suggest that that is
likely let's
well i i think that you know there's
another possibility here and that is
that
all we need written are to do is to be
able to revivify
the justice system or something like
that right revivify the ability
of governmental authority
to to work the way it has
my point basically is that all of these
uh the existing authority structures are
still premised upon the iron age
hierarchies right
so retina insofar as it creates a new
non-iron age hierarchy
will necessarily have to or necessarily
will
create the the necessary grammar or
whatever to actually start
uh reviving or revivifying the
legal systems and the other normative
system
okay but but yeah as opposed to what i
heard you say earlier
that's a much more reasonable statement
which is in line with what i thought i
was trying to say which is
we don't need to worry about those
problems necessarily they will take care
of themselves if we do a good job with
retina
because it will be able to revivify the
the the
other hierarchical structures uh
assuming that such a thing is possible
which
you know whatever i have philosophical
doubts about that but
yeah we're trying to figure out what the
scope is
yeah and what i'm trying to say is that
if we're going to have a written order
that succeeds it will have to address
the iron age hierarchy
and insofar as it does it will be
successful
in being able to revive the
the at the higher the old hierarchy
okay so that's another problem that we
have to work on then so we should put
that on the problem list
right this hierarchy problem i guess
we'll call it for the moment
that we can come up with yeah well i
think the uh in the the video that um
that we were supposed to watch like the
the comments that jordan made i think is
very useful because he ties together the
way that jonathan pejora speaks about
narrative and iron age hierarchy and the
two worlds model and how
those have all traditionally been used
to tie the whole thing together
that that's why i come at least from
having watched the
video why i think that the narrative
piece of the puzzle is actually
something to import to bring up with
respect to retinol
nobody's denying that though i think the
problem is we think that narrative is
four or five steps out
and so we don't want to try to go four
or five steps out before we do the work
of
defining problems and coming and looking
at existing solutions
etc so i i i don't understand why you're
on about this narrative thing that's all
and and you've been given that task so
that'll get solved and nobody's
because nobody's having this what i'm
saying is the iron age hierarchy problem
comes behind the narrative problem
there's a one in the same thing yes what
he's saying is the scope is larger than
previously thought yeah
so can we do this from the perspective
of
what is the foundation of biological
life for humans
you know like can we can we look at it
just from the the pure perspective of
what it is to come into this world
and the environment that one inhabits as
a child it's it
i'm not like jean piaget was
at exactly the same task that we're kind
of doing right now
and you know his work is probably
relevant to this but
there's something to the notion that you
know whatever it is to
appreciate existence um long before
we're granted these highly complex
mythopoetic narratives and long before
we even know real spoken language we're
already receiving
input about the world and about how we
should respond to it
emotionally which has a profound and
sometimes very dramatic impact
on the way in which we develop our
narrative in the future
and i think that anything that feeds
into
the right relation of the environment
upon which we enter into this world and
first receive
awareness of this world right the family
structure as it currently is
would have a profound impact on what it
is to
order and structure that thing which is
missing from
religion presently which we are trying
to find again in the religion that's not
a religion
right whatever it is that brings us in
the right relationship with each other
and with
our with our in with our environment
right which is
often defined as each other is that fair
to say that this is probably
a pretty significant design constraint
like if the structure of the family were
to change
or if the nature of how life is reared
changed or
um you know like some of these really
profound structural
geometrical changes in our culture that
that would have
a pretty significant constraint on what
it is to consider a religion
am i hearing a project in there to
figure out the relationship between
family structure
and religions because that's that's sort
of how i translated that
yeah that could be like i said i mean
yeah jean piaget's work is probably
relevant there
that that's fine i it's just another
project item on the list so
who's going to take that and run with it
right that's the question there
for the current analysis of what it is
to construct the religion that's not a
religion
right that would be a framework by which
one starts to even look for
salient information relevant information
i feel like we've just got this we've
got an overarching
uh domain to consider which is
like i'm basically condensing what i
think strewn was getting at
overall which is while
we can talk about um you know we don't
want iron age hierarchies we do we we
have to think seriously about
hierarchies in general family seems like
one example of a hierarchy that we're
going to
you know reorder
um and then obviously there's the
government
that's another hierarchy hierarchical
thing to consider
so i guess we could start putting a list
of hierarchical
topics to consider
yeah i think that's not a bad suggestion
all right so so far we've got um
narratives of other religions
and we've got hierarchies
what else needs um researching to help
define the problem and the scope of the
problem
oh yeah and we've got trying to bring
back the training of relevance
and not totalizing truth i guess
is that part of the definition of the
problem but
yeah i mean i i think the fundamental
issue we've got
that sort of causes all the other ones
is that we've totalized truth
and just forgotten relevance like we
think
i think that's the but but i mean that
almost sounds like a different way of
talking about the iron age hierarchy
well yeah i think it's that that is
definitely part of it
yeah like that those two are so like
it's actually hard to tell them apart
is it maybe maybe not let's do some
research and figure it out
instead of just assuming that they're
that tied together because i don't think
so but
you know until we have somebody
researching it we won't know
well i mean i've taken a reasonably
deep look at that kind of thing that was
a conclusion i came to
um i mean the
the main motivation for me suggesting to
john that the there's a distinction
between
intelligibility and agape let's say is
because i was trying to create a
distinction between
truth and goodness in terms of the
hierarchical demands
because it's long been a bugbear of mine
with the way that
john speaks about realism although
i have to say i'm very happy with the
way that he has actually changed the way
that he uses that term so that uh all of
these particular actually even sent me
an email today to that effect saying
it's really nice to see the way that
he's making the distinction between
reality and realness
yeah sorry i forgot where i was going
with that
well look ron if you if you have
something worked out i'd love to see a
white paper on it
but unless we have research that we can
look at that's written down that we can
read and agree on
in terms of terminology and conclusions
then
we still have zero right like we can
chat about things in voice and record it
all day long but if we can't put things
on paper that
we can agree on then we can't build a
thing and it doesn't matter what the
thing is in this case it's written are
but
that's how you build things that network
is by getting agreement
because things are written down and
people can you know really wrestle with
them
and agree to them and if you have
conclusions that sound hokey to me
but are are well thought out then you
know and you don't need to research them
hey write them down and then we'll see
if we'll see if they fit and if they fit
that's great otherwise we're not
actually making progress we're just
having
arguments over whether or not something
that somebody said may or may not be
true
right which is not going to get us
anywhere ultimately
yeah well i mean
well if you actually want the the
specifics and just look at the
alexander bard conversation
the conversation that john had because
bob went into all of the details with
respect to zoroastrianism
and how that helped to shape western
narratives
and the point is there that the
zoroastrianism or
that was what created the distinction it
was one of the first actual age
religions in that
it crafted a world view where the world
was literally separated
into the true world and the falsehood
and that was one of the ways in which
the truth was created as a totalizing
order
and so order was seen as truth and chaos
was seen as false
and that was that gave the bias towards
what was static and eternal as opposed
to what was dynamic and material let's
say
and so that like the entire iron age if
it if it is what came out of after the
bronze age collapse
is fundamentally how that zoroastrian
grammar that the two-world mythology
moved from a from a two-world chaos
order kind of paradigm to a two-world
reality slash illusion paradigm
and so that that that's where my
argument with respect to the
totalization of truth would come in
because you can actually
you can literally go up and look at the
the um
the meaning of the word uh usher and
logos and and arthur and how they
connect and they
um they all basically in
a very deep sense come back to this
notion of truth
yeah i don't disagree i'm not gonna
watch the video
i i don't know what else to tell you
other than what i said which is
unless and until we have a paper that we
can
look at all read and agree on the
conclusions of
i'm not sure we have much okay
great i can't write the paper now so
yeah
so this is a significant one
the tyre noted
which is that we should
definitely make a list
of the perennial problems
like that's literally problem
formulation
and that will definitely help with our
ecology of practices because like we can
literally just
pick them out in order to direct them
towards the solving of perennial
problems
and i literally have no idea what the
perennial problems are
i've heard the term enough times but
i've never actually remembered
what they are well i think that an
example would be like horror
when you are when your life is overcome
by horror because
all of the the things that you thought
made sense no longer make sense anymore
and you don't know where you are
like that's a perennial problem because
it's something that everybody can face
during the
and there's nothing there's nothing you
can do to get rid of the perennialness
of the problem
and so there's things like that
self-deception um
foolishness in general um
now i suppose you know but i mean it can
be it can also be things like grief you
know because
uh having to deal with death is a
perennial problem
it's a good point we can have some kind
of macro and micro perennial problems
right and and i i would say that
from a therapeutic perspective you would
want like a sweeter response
and and a way of figuring out how to tie
those responses together
so that you could actually give
i don't know maybe you don't but at
least in theory you could potentially
have a one-size-fits-all kind of a
solution
i don't know if you'd want to go down
that route
guess we'll see
yeah you certainly need to do a bunch of
research on
perennial problems that's a good idea
i'm not sure they're going to map it all
to the ecology
just based on what i understand of it
but you know
we have to list them to find out right
and then we'll again
we still have to schematize the ecology
but that's actually going to get work
done soon so
um yeah the if if the perennial solving
the perennial problems is
part of the definition of written r and
i think that's
probably as close to an axiomatic
statement as we can make at this point
um then that should be pretty high on
the list of things to get
at least a handle on if if we can't sort
it out i think that john has actually
commented on this before that
nobody actually has a complete list to
some extent
and i don't remember the context or or
you know if i'm remembering accurately
at all but
yeah it would be helpful to at least
have an idea of what all the
all the possible levels of perennial
problem are
and and get some kind of handle on
what might be able to to fix that within
uh that
that can be done within the religion
side
i've just i've just considered
so strewn mentioned that obviously one
of our
perennial problems is death but
it feels like there's a genre
of thing we have to address that isn't
exactly a problem
like birth like we celebrate
births and it feels like that's going to
be
like we need to include something like
that
but it doesn't feel like that's solving
a problem
exactly and yet
so that there's sort of something
that's on the same level as problems
that we need to kind of formulate
that we might address say goodness
i mean well i mean you're talking about
birth
and you know when you when it comes to
the bronze age religions
they were all about fertility and birth
and creation
like the the partaking in the generative
aspect of life was to partake in
sacredness
literally and so you know like the
the the the bronze age festivals and the
rituals and everything
were all around maximizing fertility
wonder all of them but like a good
portion of them at least
yeah i don't i don't know if you're
getting at a problem per se
i mean it can be framed as a problem
right so the
the well i would say not having the
thing could be a problem
yes as i was saying you can reformula
reformulate it as a problem right but
it's the something like
all of the we need to come up with a set
of all of the things
that are that positively
generate
not not just people and not just healthy
families for example to tyler's point
but but also healthy
cultures and healthy societies if we can
make a
distinction there and perhaps we can
make more distinctions but it's
something along those lines
i think that would be a good list to
have too right so you have a list of
generative things and then you have a
list of
uh blocker things in essence which are
the perennial problems
right and then you you you need to
define some progression
right and then because as you go through
life right obviously as you get towards
the end of your life you worry about
your own death not just everybody else's
so i think that's worthy of having some
research done on it
uh and that would tie nicely into what
tyler was talking about
okay so i dropped out for a bit there um
so strong's looking into the narrative
of other religions
um what other um subsections do we have
and do we have anyone who's decided they
want to work on them
well we just we just discussed um
perennial problems and then a kind of
positive version like
i can't remember what don't know what
we're going to call it yet but yeah
i i'm quite interested in looking at
perennial problems
so
i'll probably take that up
so what are we calling it then
protective factors or something like
that
things that help prevent the problems or
mitigate the problems
mitigating factors alleviation
well we want the list first we want to
define
the perennial problems perennial problem
formulation
before we can think about the you know
solutions but i
i think the ecology of practices is
probably going to be
the main solution to perennial problems
yeah and to your point we need a name
for the things that are generative
you know of society i don't know if
they're positively generative of
culture or something like that right but
it's bigger than just culture obviously
societies and cultures protective
influences
well i don't know just a degenerative
one right things like birth and
fertility and
you know uh you know raised positive
raising of children
right positive development of families
to tyler's point about relationships
right
positive relationships at the family
level which engender positive
relationships at the community level
etc all the way up to as far as you need
to go
so those are the things that are stopped
by the perennial problems
right so you need to know what the
things are that are generating the
society and the culture and etc
and and you need the list of perennial
problems that are preventing those from
either unfolding at all or unfolding
healthily or both
something like that so those are two
different projects that
sort of interrelate and you know maybe
tyler's stuff folds in
right there or something around you know
how relationships and
and all that it sounds uh very similar
but yeah if you don't engender not only
a way to to be
fertile but to but to a positive way to
be fertile but
but also to to have good parenting
uh uh skills or whatever that that are
positively generative
right and regenerative then yeah you've
definitely got a a problem that's not a
perennial problem but created by your
by your system sometimes
so i've note i've noticed that another
one of my notes
kind of is some
problem formulation that
john mentioned which is his way of
explaining it was religions tend to fall
into semantic complexity
and the equivocation that results from
that causes a lot of problems
so that seems to raise
the necessity for a
a nice clean consistent
well like set of terms to refer to
things
obviously that can uh
i can probably tie into the whole uh
universal religious language that's sort
of been alluded to
where we try to get all the like the
religions speaking to each other
if we can have a religion a a language
where we can talk about
all the religions at once essentially in
the same terms
and our own the retina in the end that
would be pretty good
yeah uh in the video that was uh where
john komsky uh
commented on kamsky's universal grammar
and how it was constructed via ai right
yeah yeah yeah no i also had that in my
notes um and yeah i basically wanted to
make a very similar point
right you could compile i'm sorry sure
um yeah i was just gonna say uh
well i was just gonna add to so you can
actually go ahead um i don't know
well you're just yeah just compiling a
synonymous list
right like when i say soul
and when i say opman when i say what am
i really meaning when i say all these
things according to each of the
frameworks
and then if there's a commonality of
that notion
having a good list of synonyms and then
being able to extract from that group
the essence right
kind of maintain the continuity of of uh
of understanding across the you know the
major
religious modalities yeah that would be
good
yeah yeah that's that's that's building
the glass i think
um but you know actually for in terms of
having religion speak to each other
it won't be enough to have the terms
like utman and soul you know it won't
just be
what those terms are it will be what
those terms are in
uh rel or in comparison to other terms
within the same language
and then the the the relative
differences in terms of the
relationships
will be what tells you how to navigate
between the
languages of the religion i think that
will probably be true in cases of
deeply integrated concepts and concepts
that are inherently ambiguous
but there are probably quite a few that
you can that are that are well
constellated
right like it's like the notion of a
soul um
the notion of an afterlife notion of
uh history and all this stuff right well
i would say yes and no because the issue
is it's like um
you know take buddhism versus
christianity for example it's like they
both have a
an idea of a soul but they both have an
idea of a soul
that that um where the soul
is in some sense important in terms of
the journey towards heaven
but the journey towards heaven is very
very different
in terms of buddhism and christianity so
the way that
heaven influences the idea of a soul is
very very important
and it's those kinds of differences
because
you're right to some degree with the
concepts but the the trick comes in
because the religions are always like a
whole system with a world view and they
they work by tying the concept together
so it's always a highly systematized
thing
and so to actually get at the
functionality it's not enough to just
get at the concept you actually have to
get at the con
the relationships between the concepts
as well
yes right so i think like metaphysically
we're going to have to make some
sacrifices and that will always be true
in order to yeah well well i i think
what the question there would be is like
in terms of metaphysics
what are there any commonalities between
all of the religions that we can
identify
well this is the
because it's not just the commonalities
of content but it's also the
commonalities of context
and right all of it what is there any
commonality we can identify whatsoever
because if there isn't any commonality
then we don't have a hope of
constructing a universal grammar
we have to look for some kind of common
feature or
something that that we can that we can
use as the first step
if we have that then everything else can
more or less follow
okay i don't know that might be getting
like a couple of steps ahead of
i really again i think it has a lot to
do with
so from my own perspective and i'll just
interject this um
and then i probably have to take off but
there's very much of maslow's hierarchy
if there if there are any hierarchies it
has to do with precedent
that which has to exist prior to the
construction of any higher thing
and that which feeds into right so
there's there are deep
interrelationships that stack up in that
way and
if one is you know deeply unable to
provide food
it makes it very difficult for you to
have any interest in you know any amount
of
of uh religious mythopoetic
structure it's it's it's difficult to
obtain meaning from these kinds of
things
but as you ascend up into higher and
higher orders of complexity and
interrelatedness at the social layer you
need
you need more and more stories and more
and more narratives and more and more
propositions to teach about how those
relationships are to function
in the more complex space
so do you want to look at hierarchies
then
well we already discussed hierarchies
but it has more to do with like
where individuals are in their own
particular hierarchy
and then whether or not where they're
situated
currently is providing it's meeting the
needs of
of what their distressed environment
appears as
it's not just that hierarchy by the way
there's something else that happens it's
a little more common
in this space which has to do with uh
world views
and i'll use just the low resolution
left and right hemispherical
preferences but it's very difficult to
get
people to agree upon certain kinds
of moral and ethical considerations
based on these these radically different
views of analyzing the world so
um yeah that often is you could consider
that a perennial
problem in the construction of a shared
mythopoetic structure
yeah well i would agree with that but
that's exactly
you see that that's where you'd have to
look
and see with even within the different
views and the conflicting views can you
where are the commonalities at least not
in terms of what they say
but in terms of the way that they speak
because if you can't get that then the
idea of of having a universal
religious grammar will work because you
will always have
um there will always be no matter what
kind of
grammar you create to tie religions
together
there will always be at least one
religion that sits outside of your
grammar
okay so what else do we need to look at
to define the scope of the problem
i think we've got a lot to chew on
already maybe we've got death we've got
hierarchies we've got narrative
yeah i'm going to try and go back and
write all of this down
afterwards that's the point yeah so it's
so cool
the main points i've got is that bruins
looking at the narrative of other
religions which
which i'm guessing will um include the
um the grammar and the terms that
they're using and their world views
and their metaphysics and
veloskin's looking at the perennial
problem
and if we're having someone look at
perennial problems do we need someone to
be looking at
the the thing that we haven't
got a definition for yet the good parts
of life
the things that are um are blocked by
the problems
no i thought maybe we can call them like
perennial needs
i don't know
[Music]
would you guys uh see community
as solving a problem
exactly yeah absolutely yeah
okay for sure yes perennial solutions
well no it's it's me it's the drivers
right it's the
forward drivers that that are blocked by
the problems
all right perennial needs sounds good to
me
and then i think tyler wanted to do
relationships
right this piagetian uh
take on things which i think is relevant
okay so strewn's got narratives of other
religions
tyler's got um hierarchies relationships
so often's got
perennial problems um does anyone want
to do perennial needs
am i grabbing that one then
because like we should do problems and
needs intense if you want it
yes it's kind of kind of combined but
it's it's two sides of the same problem
right
besides the same thing i don't i don't
think so
exactly but what i would say is that if
they match up
you have a better chance of of realizing
that you have complete lists on both
sides
so it's certainly worth at least
approaching them there's different
things
instead of trying so if i have my list
and veloskin has his list then we come
together and we're like wait a sec
there's five things on my list that
don't match up with any of the things on
your list and vice versa then
we've missed something but we'll find
that we'll find the other part
yeah i doubt it'll be that it won't be
that straightforward
yeah yeah it won't be that clear that
that's the
idea yeah yeah well the the
the the list of perennial problems will
basically be a list of things to avoid
the list of perennial needs will
basically be a list of things
should try and get so yeah there will be
like there will be opposites but like
you i think you won't find an overlap of
of the same things
you will find an overlap of opposition
yeah restrict overlap but there will be
some things that are related
yeah definitely okay well i've got
perennial needs then
well i i i saw the pruning problems as
something we're trying to solve like
we're not trying to
we are trying to avoid self-esteem
right now we're trying to define what
the problems are right
i don't know if you can solve a
perennial problem i think that the
goal must be to cope with the problem
yeah i
i i i know what you mean it's not we're
not going to sort of finally
extinguish the perennial problems from
the universe you're not going to fix
death
no yeah but we're going to respond
like maybe we should use john's town we
will need to address the premier commons
yeah responding to the perennial problem
yeah
yeah but just the project is just to get
the lists done
first and then worry about what to do
with them
yeah we're defining the problem first
and so we're
looking into the problem more to define
it better
right okay so do we ask
for separate channels for these four
sections within retina
no i think you can just i mean
because like we're seeing channels
anyway
yeah i don't i don't know the channels
are what you need necessarily i think if
you're going to have discussions you can
just have it in the written our channel
for now
and then what the output of this should
be something
like a report or a write-up
or something that again people can look
at and get agreement on
right okay so maybe like a bunch uh
different pinned documents and then um
that people will cut people can come and
say okay i want help with this i want to
help with that
right
right and then we'll pin a document
called you know
current research or something right and
then
list who's in charge of the research and
then if people want to help they can
help or
there's something that isn't assigned
with a person in charge they can
volunteer to take charge for example
so we need an organizing document and
then we'll each create a
document on the section we're working on
and
put those in there does that make sense
yeah or we can have them as google docs
or whatever yeah we can certainly work
on the technology is not important right
it's just just understanding what the
output should be
and that is more important
all right awesome i've got to go about
now so
good luck if you're continuing and if
not and i'll see you guys next week
i'm going to keep recording for about
another hour i'm going to stop
as well what else is there to be
discussed
well i'm going to throw this word in
and everyone else is going to tell me
the answers because i'm not
sure i really can say much about it um
so scalability we want it to be able to
fit into
like every part of society so different
socio-economic classes
as well as you know developmental stages
childhood adulthood and so on
well i have something to say about that
but i'll sound like a broken record so
it won't
so scalability in general is a
multivariate thing
right so there's scalability of how you
hello
oh i thought that was me cutting out so
i was just about to reconnect
yeah sorry about that scalability
along many lines right so the
availability of audience
scalability of how you spread
the word right within that audience so
that
has obviously right and then there's
the scalability around how it's accessed
right to accommodate the different
audiences so same thing might have four
or five access points for example
based on you know what appeals to
different groups
yeah i've already mentioned the idea of
kind of trying to make different hooks
for different temperaments or something
yeah and just being able to spread it
right like how do you get it
the people who need it sort of a thing
right
so when we're talking about ecology of
practices
that the word always comes up is
scalability
and the context for scalability there is
how do we spread the ecology of
practices to a lot of people even
assuming they want to engage right we're
not even getting into the
how do we make it appealing to a lot of
people we're
we're getting let's assume everybody
wanted this
how the heck would we get into all these
people that's because that's just one
variable in the scalability
problem
are you hoping to discuss scalability in
general or just get a better handle on
scalability or
you know what's your goal in bringing it
up to begin with
it just seems pretty important
but i also feel like i'm just supremely
ignorant and i was interested
to see if anybody had any good thoughts
on it
but anyway well i think
i mean i'm quite familiar with what paul
had to say about scalability
because he always mentions how jesus
scales right
um and the thing that he says that
what's remarkable about jesus
is that he died and
he had a couple of uh the fishermen or
whatever you know basically illiterate
people
who were his witnesses and they wrote
his story down
ended up basically taking over the whole
world and it lasted for
well today 2 000 years so that's
something that scales
because it works for to basically work
for an entire people to live
the way that jesus said and so
paul's concern with respect to
scalability and written or
would be uh yeah well you know can it
actually do something
like what jesus accomplished and how
would you actually go about accomplish
if you were in his shoes or if you you
know you had that opportunity
how would you go about doing it what
would you
right so that's time scalability plus
audience scalability
plus um reproductive scalability i
suppose
yeah well that's that's sort of time
scalability right time scalability
implies that you have to change
or evolve or whatever with the as
as as things on the ground change right
and that that implies that
in order to do that you need some sort
of interactive feedback mechanism so
that you're
in touch with the people that you're
serving
uh and yeah i i i don't disagree but um
i was more meaning like you know you
have the individual then you have the
town then you have the state and you
have the country then you have the world
like that kind of reproduction but yeah
that's hierarchical scalability
my answer to you depends on whether or
not i'm supposed to be attacking the
idea of an iron age hierarchy or not
like that that that's fraud territory i
yeah i know i i i understand that
so it's
all right so to bridge that gap why
don't we call it structural scalability
is that fair yeah i could live with that
yeah
sure all right so that's another type of
scalability you want to watch out for
yeah so that happens very much so so
i've
said a bunch of scalability for you is
that is that good for
discussing scalability or do you need
more or do you want more
on that i don't think that's exhaustive
but at least it gives us an idea of how
big the scalability issue is because
it's one word that means
lots of things with multiple dimensions
i think he was asking you velocin i was
i see
i i'm sort of mildly disturbed by
just being seen as a leader right now
well you brought up the word i wasn't i
wasn't implying anything i was just
trying to find out if
that helped you with with what your goal
was in bringing up the word or not
yeah i'm just poking the collective and
just
seeing what happens oh crap how do i
hurt these cats i don't hate these cats
no well i think it's i mean it's a it's
a reasonable thing to bring up
certainly oh yeah
i mean if the goal was just to create a
bunch of a bunch of angry hornets that
you know you created two angry hornets
congratulations
yeah the thing that i have in brackets
for my notes was that i think that
heroes in some sense have something to
do with scalability
there's
this there's something about the way
that we craft heroes within stories that
is very very sticky and we pay attention
to it and we remain
and i think it might have something to
do with the fact that
you know that was the way we had to tell
stories in order to
transmit our old traditions before we
had writing and so
it seems to me that the that our ability
to pay attention to particular
characters would be
it could be something that has evolved
so that we actually are able better able
to remember
the necessary features of a hero that if
we try and embody
will lead us to success in our life
and i think if we're going to have
something that scales we're going to
have to have something that actually
can can appropriate the
the evolutionary structures that have to
do with with hero formulation
and could be perhaps you can tell me if
it's already been done but
we we're going to have the hero
definitely
maybe we could have like the
society hero so like the
[Music]
like the society's version of a hero
you mean like jesus collective hero like
jesus is a individual that individuals
emulate
okay maybe we could have sort of a
vision for what our society is meant to
be
i would say jesus was not a hero
yeah okay but that's kind of besides the
point um
the like what would what would a
collective hero look like
exactly like is it is it a group of
people
or is it one person that is just like
group like or what are you talking about
well we've got the the hero individual
who's like the ideal of a person
maybe yeah so but you want the idea of a
collective but no
right so but i'm asking you how how
would you go about
talking about that ideal
but i think there's an assumption
there's an assumption built in there
that that
that the collective is not an emerging
property of a bunch of people acting in
heroic fashion
yeah well that that's exactly it's the
the difficulties because like
if you're talking about collective isn't
it a bunch of people
right right so so if if the collective
is just a bunch of people
and they cohere to the degree that their
heroes
which can be different have enough
similarities
to engender cohesion then it's
more or less an emerging property that
you can't control directly but you
control indirect i mean
jordan peterson makes this point right
like if everybody just
works on themselves then the world will
magically be a better place and that is
necessarily true but
uh he doesn't focus on on like that mid
level
like don't don't don't he says don't go
out and try to make the
society a better place just make
yourself a better a better person and
everything will take care of itself
yeah i think um
well the closest that i can think of to
this um
the collective idea would be
david gamel's novels the
however
the draenei tales um because there he
had the
he did like a weird neoplatonic thing
with the thirty
um and there were these thirty uh
like warrior priest type things um and
they had these spiritual powers but they
also had excellent
uh martial combatability and then they
would basically go
you know in into a war and all except
one of them would die
but then in the story itself like one of
the things that the city could do
was to spiritually join in to form the
one
and i mean well that's where the
neoplaton neoplatonism comes in because
like it's all of those neoplatonic
tropes but
i suppose you could kind of maybe
symbolize
a collective hero as a hero that is
constructed out of
let's say 30 individuals and becomes you
know one individual
out of the individuals you know so it's
like a it's a collective but it is an
individual at the same time
but yeah i don't know if if you don't
like
that's about the only way that i could
think of going about
the sort of thing that you're talking
about it's a curtain
maybe the hero archetype itself mediates
between
being a good person and
being so in a way that makes a good
community
yeah well that that yeah that that's the
at least that was was the idea behind
christianity i think
uh yeah also deep degree uh buddhism uh
taoism i'm not so sure about um
and yeah i think that's certainly true
right like like heroes go out and get
something for the benefit of the
community
and the thing that they the thing that
they're doing
is sacrificing their potential in the
future
right to uh to benefit the community
so that is communal in nature generally
it's not like
because heroes generally don't tend to
be uh
selfish right by definition if they're
selfish they're not good heroes
um i don't know but that that's
debatable
generally generally
i used all the weasel words i could well
i i definitely think look
that there is a
especially with respect to heroism it is
a question of how do you sacrifice
heroic
i think christianity is is probably the
religion that is most
most focused upon that question
there's a lot of forms of sacrifice
right
like right but but jesus's sacrifice is
the ultimate sacrifice right so it's
like the
well yeah like how do you like like
christianity is really trying to
to give the the answer to like how do
you sacrifice properly yourself
um
it doesn't focus on one it doesn't focus
on the one
sacrifice though right and i think that
would be a deep mistake
right i mean yeah you have to talk about
the ultimate sacrifice but
you don't you don't build your society
based on
you know the ultimate sacrifice because
that's called a death cult and i i don't
think that's the direction we want to go
in you can correct me if i'm wrong but
i'm fairly sure
we're in agreement that that would be
bad so let's not do that
um so yeah i mean
um yeah you know there's
and right who sacrifices his wildness to
engage in a bunch of other adventures
in some sense right so there's
definitely different levels of sacrifice
and different types of sacrifice and
and reasons not to make those sacrifices
and and
examples in in mythos where one hero
makes one sacrificial choice and the
other makes
basically the opposite type of a choice
and
you just get one right like you want
this guy to be here or this guy because
you can't make both sacrifices
so yeah i think that's important right
yeah there are lots of examples yeah
yeah i know i mean that yeah that it's
definitely an ongoing conversation
but i think i mean yeah i think like a
big part of religion is about
um recording that conversation
keeping the spirit of the conversation
alive
right well we have a way to keep spirits
of conversations alive so
that's already solved thank goodness
like um humans have a tendency to try
and remember the things that are worth
sacrificing for
and so that you know there but it's like
it's our earlier debates you know people
will always
they will value different things so
they'll think different things are worth
sacrificing
right but the hero within this
context i guess is the the thing that
actually
shows us what the sacrifice looks like
so that we can do it ourselves if we
actually agree with
what it's supposed to yeah your
story will be what tells us the like how
the whole thing plays out again
right it gives us a template for an
acting at the same time
so yeah we get to see what might be we
get to see all the possibilities
right and then we get to see the outcome
based on success and
and and to paul's bender clay's point
right you want to see the outcome
based on failure too and you know we
kind of missed some of that
yeah well um i think uh john also said
something similar because
the greek stories around hubris people
forget their mortality
you know they forget their mistakes
right i think yeah
that that's definitely i wonder i
suppose that would be part of the
perennial problem
possibly yeah yeah i mean you're going
to have a bunch of
opposite too much humility too little
humility
right those are probably perennial
problems navigating humility
i wonder what too much humility actually
looks like
a question well it's an underestimation
of your
capacities there's a lot of people right
in fact my friend has it he
he underestimates his abilities and it
makes him sort of
oh yeah no i agree yeah
you don't want to prematurely close on
your potential if you don't if you don't
have to
yeah well in my opinion generally
self-potentialization
you're trying i agree with that actually
earlier when you said the hero
sacrifices potential in the future i was
like no no
no no no
can i offer i get what you're trying to
say though yeah
yeah you say uh so i'm not disagreeing
with anybody i'm just offering
a different lens or or let's say
put a different color over the light to
reveal
different things if you've ever looked
at like a flannel shirt
in a nightclub as the lights change
the pattern on the shirt also changes so
sometimes
if just offering different things you
can kind of reframe your perception but
as you guys are talking about this um
my mind is going to a different place
so sacrifice is on my mind as the first
primary thing
but in my mind sacrifice is a
function of productivity right so
a hero is a champion what are champions
what makes someone a champion they have
to win
right often is said pride comes before
the fall that's not actually true pride
comes after the win
and so um if we have pride in our heroes
it's because they have done
something productive um oftentimes
talk is not productive uh forming
committees
is not productive um uh
writing books is not productive
publishing
books is productive right so
there's a there is a real world
benefit to actually producing
something that can be held in your hand
and
um i think sacrifice has that quality
where
sacrifice for its own sake is stupid
that's
essentially fasting and no one holds a
hero in highest regard simply because he
fasted enough
right gandhi might be an exception but
he was also quite a piece of shit so
like the um
i guess what i'm trying to offer is that
i i do believe that there is a
productivity to heroism
and and there has to be a win you have
to be the champion
and it doesn't really matter how you got
there either
if you win and your opponents are dead
you're the hero
regardless of how of of what you did to
get there and as long as you're
supplying
some level of productivity for the
audience they are going to hold you as a
hero now the other thing i wanted to
mention was
um heroes have a mysterious quality to
them
part of what makes a hero a hero is that
they are a champion but very little is
actually known
about their thought process their
motivations
or what drives them and that's what
really
endears us to the hero is that we don't
know where their source of power comes
from
we don't know if they they have this
extra
judicial quality to them like like think
of hercules right
he was a demigod he had the blood of the
gods in him
something that humans can't actually
achieve and so
that hero was able to be productive in
ways that other peoples weren't
leading to him to be a champion now that
might be complete and utter horseshit i
just wanted to put it out there just to
let your minds start spinning
um well i just wanted to on the first
point sort of uh respond because
um the word sacrifice literally means to
make sacred so in terms of the
productivity
like yeah making it's not making if it
isn't productive
so sacrifice is making sacred therefore
sacrifice has to be productive
um yeah basically i agree with you 100
it means to cause to be sacred by the
way
in the sense of make sacred
not make sacredly um
no no well i mean like artifices like
you know if you if you if
that's making right so sacrifices is
another kind of making
yeah well
well i guess i'm just curious what
what's the distinction between making
and causing
well what i presume you're saying make
sacred from like did i tell you that it
means that or did you
find that yourself no i think you told
me
yeah um when i say make sacred i meant
like cause to be sacred like i make
that that's i meant that in that sense
in the english word of make
like cause to be your cause too
yeah like like a maker like if you
produce the thing you literally made it
yeah but it's like i i'm making
something sacred
i caused it to be sacred i caused it to
have a certain
trait right but like
what i'm trying to say is ultimately if
you go back to the oldest ideas of
sacrifice right it's always a death but
it's a death that serves life
it's a it's you you kill the thing in
such a way that it that it actually
makes it serve life and so it's always a
um yeah so
it's the i don't know really how to
like it it's a way to to
basically deal with death in a way that
that subverts it i guess
and that that was the i like the the
idol the the idea of sacredness was
was the was to was to recover the hole
with you know like to heal and so you
the the sacrifice is the death that
allows you to heal
in other words it's like a it's a it's a
weird kind of a paradox but surprise i
can tell that that was
sort of the idea behind it and so it's
the
destruction in the name of creation
right but then so you you you make the
creation through the destruction right
that's the that's what you're producing
and so the idea of a sacrifice
um to what sesame
i don't know i'm probably not
pronouncing that for wrong but anyway
but um
what he said you know about the the the
the thing having to be productive it's
like if you're just sacrificing for no
reason whatsoever that doesn't serve the
purpose of use
the question is like when is it actually
you know like
when is it a good idea to kill yourself
that's the the the whole idea about
sacrificing
is an attempt to actually answer that
question
and it is something that you know like a
human presumably would want to know what
what
is worth dying at least in principle i
don't know
maybe somebody thinks well that thing is
worth dying for i don't know but i think
that
like if you i don't think you've fully
come to terms with your mortality if
there's nothing
on the list that you aren't willing to
die for
i also wanted to disagree with the idea
that we just don't understand the hero
i mean like maybe that's true of many
hero stories but uh sort of defeats
the point of having the hero story if
you don't actually know what makes them
a hero
so no to to well
yes and no the issue is that if you
don't say anything about the hero then
any then everybody can sympathize they
can put themselves in the hero's shoes
because the absence of details just
allows them to place
themselves in the hero so that's a it's
a it's a narrative trick
if you're trying to create a a character
or a hero that everybody can relate to
that's a great way of doing it
like harry potter is a very strong
example like
he's almost featureless but he
but he like except he's the boy who
lived but like everything about him
like he's a very silent character he's
not like ron or hermione
which are you know their characters are
very very well defined
so there isn't elements of truth to that
but i agree with you i don't think that
you
if you really uh
describing hero who's supposed to
succeed and is supposed to
tell people something useful about life
then you'll need to shade in all of
those details
like it's not going to work any other
way
do you think brad weinstein is a hero
uh he sacrificed
he championed he was productive and he
is mysterious
well he certainly has has heroism about
him
i don't know if he's a hero if he's a
martyr but yeah
seems more like a martyr to me i'm not
sure i'm sold on that particular set of
features of heroes so
martyr has to be killed
you're taking the sacrifice thing all
the way to the end when you really don't
need to we sacrifice all kinds of things
all the time and different heroes
sacrifice different things that actually
aren't there live
and it worked out fine so
yeah i mean i understand going to the
extremes specialty of mine but in this
case it's probably maladaptive
he obtained like 10 years salary from
that what
what did he martyr
losing his job was the best thing that
could have happened to him i don't see
the no no no no no first of all trading
cash
for something like a pension or a stable
job is the dumbest thing you can do
i mean it's just pig ignore to take cash
over even much more cash
it's stupid right that's that's why
people go bankrupt because they don't
understand the value of having
income over having capital today
right so yeah he lost a very good job
that he liked
and he doesn't get to do what he most
liked in the world
i would say it's almost certain that
some people will hear a worship
the kind of person that brett is
but i would not consider him a hero
it's very interesting because he hits
all the points that you guys are
touching on
it's it's very interesting to me when i
talk to people on these servers how
how they're able to classify somebody
they're able to kind of paint this
picture
right and then i provide an example that
fits that picture and no no not that guy
but we just don't like him right and
it's like
it it's interesting i just i disagree
with these values so therefore i don't
really consider it
like i'm not sure that he sacrificed
himself for the right things and so
therefore i'm critical of it
it doesn't matter how he ended up in in
the
in the grand scheme of things with
respect to how wealthy is and everything
like uh if if you're asking me
did he uh did he succeed financially
through what he did
yes but i don't i don't i don't see how
that has to
what that has to do with his heroism per
se and like
he's provided leadership to many
young men and women who are seeking
roles in science
are entering academia his story has been
dispute that i i fully acknowledge it
but i'm saying
i'm not sure that that particular role
that he's trying to play
is a let's call it it's not
evolutionarily adapted
opinion so i'm suspicious of it so your
hero has to also be perfect then
nobody said anything about him and we
also weren't trying to explain what made
a hero
and what did right we did we never we
never settled on that definition
so i don't know why you're making that
characterization
it's conversation
i haven't unless it's not sorry
can you hear me right now yes yes
i have a question what's the difference
between an alchemist
hero earlier oh
ability um transcending suffering
feedback loop
sorry you're cutting out a little bit so
oh sending suffering
now you're cutting somebody's cutting
all i heard was alchemist and in terms
of heroism
i can see that like an alchemist is
somebody
like a transformative individual so
there's there's a strong
aspect of heroism to them at least
conceptually like that that is
i think at least some people try to
describe alchemy
heroes in in terms of their personal
spiritual journeys
like that that was the or at least the
magician within alchemy
like well you know the alchemist in the
magicians like
almost the same thing but um the the
personal well somebody would
at least in theory you know there was
like the idea that they would be
initiated by another alchemist
or or the writings of another outcome
and then they'll go on their own
their own journey because of it but like
the the whole thing does have a a
heroic kind of romantic streak about
definitely
i don't know if that speaks to what um
lynn was trying to say or not but
that's what i could the sense that i
could get from
i just just wanted to we've got like 20
minutes before i finish the recording so
i'm going to say
does anyone did is anyone else here
other than the
three that have basically talked the
entire time got any uh
notes that they're busting to express or
thoughts on what's been said so far
hey guys i've been listening for a while
uh a lot of thoughts
a lot of thoughts
trying to determine if they should just
remain as thoughts and trying to figure
out
what to be said um
let me do one thing
just to go back to the initial point of
the discussion
a religion that's not a religion and i
definitely attracted to that the more i
do these practices
the meditation the yoga the reading
the the being the the doing of the
philosophy
that's imbued with such
history and
connects me to this intense
ancient it just connects me to my
ancestors in some way
it connects me with my humanity
transcends my identity
and allows me to deep
like to reach into some capacity for
for some kind of self-actualization
it seems like such a good process
and then you know i'm interested in
these
discussions about the religion that's
not a religion
but the mode of communication and the
process of
development just hinges on
these structures that i perceive
as well worn out
inevitably the conversation turns to
hierarchy
organization self-organization some form
of auditing
um project management you know
um and
it's just interesting how uh like i i
don't doubt that there's gonna be some
development
and things to be
mined in that direction but what i think
i also heard at the beginning was that
the the practice the dialogues the
philosophia
is really perhaps the heart of the way
into a great synthesis of
what matters and
despite the heart of you know
despite the fact that usually
the heart of these practices is sort of
delving into this unknowingness this uh
this inability to
to resolve matters
so i guess
that's kind of what i have to say i
appreciate all you guys that i'm just
getting to know the server more and more
but
uh yeah that's that's all
well hi and welcome hope you enjoy your
stay
yeah yeah it's uh it's good i i hope
it's it'll continue to be a space for
for open dialogue and
and a good faith of
the of this course in practice
i think you can call it velocity and i
don't think that the last 15 minutes
yeah i was thinking at least not in
terms of recording all right